Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection FILMS.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Transport Workers Union of America Films, 1930-1977; 34.5 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons and 177 film cans; 13.3 Gigabytes in 18 digital files
  - Subseries I.A. Films, 1930-1977
    - Twenty-Nine Days to Victory, 1953
      - Outtakes (Box 19, Film canister c112, 16mm film reels 001_0421)
        Matthew Guinan speaking at a podium, giving a detailed report on strike negotiations with the company.
      - Outtakes (Box 19, Film canister c112, 16mm film reels 001_0422)
        Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
        Poor audio quality.
        Gustav Faber speaking at podium to striking members.
      - Outtakes (Box 19, Film canister c112, 16mm film reels 001_0423)
        Press conference with Michael Quill, Matthew Guinan and Dan Gilmartin.
      - Outtakes (Box 19, Film canister c112, 16mm film reels 001_0424)
        Matthew Guinan reading to a meeting a letter or telegram of support for 1953 New York City private bus lines strike from Walter Reuther of the CIO.
      - Outtakes (Box 19, Film canister c112, 16mm film reels 001_0425)
        Man speaking about demand for a 40-hour week with no reduction in pay. A second man speaks, out of synch.
      - Outtakes (Box 19, Film canister c112, 16mm film reels 001_0426)
        Press conference featuring Michael Quill, Ellis Van Riper, and Matthew Guinan. Quill makes a statement giving the TWU's reaction to proposed lay-offs by the Board of Transportation, and describes work stoppages that took place in reaction to these proposals. From the context it appears that this was pre-strike in 1953.
      - Outtakes (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0437)
        Allan Haywood of the CIO speaks in support of New York City bus strike and need for 40-hour week for New York City and Philadelphia bus drivers.
      - Outtakes (Film canister c158, 16mm film reels 001_0179, Film canister c157, 16mm film reels 001_0344)
        Michael Quill speaks at televised press conference and mass meeting.
      - Outtakes (Box 16, Film canister c140, 16mm film reels 001_0392, 001_0393)
      - Soundtrack and outtakes (Film canister c173, 16mm film reels 001_0201)
        Includes synch soundtrack for the documentary. Also includes trims and outtakes, specifically from the sequence in which Transport Workers Union leaders report to the membership on the progress of the strike at an outdoor rally on Murray Street.
      - Supplementary footage (Box 27, 16mm film reels 001_0831)
        See the video reproduction cuid36996 in Subseries I.B.
        Mixed trims and outtakes, including shots of street signs in New York City, audiences at Transport Workers Union meetings, TWU leaders addressing meetings, several different press conferences with Michael Quill, pickets against the Pennsylvanian Railroad, and an address by Michael Quill to members on the union.
      - Trims (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0439)
        Michael Quill makes a statement addressed to general public supporting Robert Wagner Jr.'s candidacy for mayor of New York City.
      - Trims (Box 21, 16mm film reels 001_0438)
        Includes exteriors of apartment buildings and of New York City school; footage relating to Robert Wagner, Jr.'s New York mayoral election campaign; Michael Quill addressing mass meeting of Transport Workers Union Local 100 members on strike.
    - Bus Strike -- Mass Meeting, 1953-1954 (Film canister c174, 16mm film reels 001_0192, 001_0193)
      Depicts a mass meeting during the 1953 New York City private bus lines strike.
    - Compilation of Mass Meetings and Press Releases, 1953-1954 (Film canister c175, 16mm film reels 001_0195)
      TWU Local 100 mass meeting during 1953 New York City bus strike; Transport Workers Union memorial meeting for Allan Haywood; filmed press releases by Michael Quill; Transport Workers Union officials in front of New York City Bar Association headquarters.
    - The Best is Yet to Come, 1967
      A documentary produced by the Transport Workers Union that reviews history of the union, its status ca. 1967, and its future.
      - Complete film (Film canister c195, 16mm film reels 001_0153, 001_0154)
        Part one: 001_0154; Part two: 001_0153.
      - Complete film (Box 34, 16mm film reels 001_0276)
      - 30th Anniversary Cutaways, 1964 (Film canister c175, 16mm film reels 001_0194)
      - 30th Anniversary Speeches, 1964 (Film canister c180, 16mm film reels 001_0199)
        Speeches at the 30th Anniversary celebration of the Transport Workers Union. Michael Quill speaks for the bulk of the roll, reminiscing about early days of the union.
      - 30th Anniversary Speeches, 1964 (Film canister c74, 16mm film reels 001_0303)
        See the video reproduction cuid1029 in Subseries I.B.
        Leaders of the Transport Workers Union speak at its 30th Anniversary Convention; New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr. makes an address.
      - 30th Anniversary Speeches, 1964 (Box 31, 16mm film reels 001_0320)
        Speeches at the 30th Anniversary celebration of the Transport Workers Union, held at the Americana Hotel in New York City in 1964. Most of the roll is Michael Quill speaking.
      - Bus Driver Interview (Film canister c156, 16mm film reels 001_0207)
        Tom Costigan interviews bus driver.
      - Bus Footage (Film canister c117, 16mm film reels 001_0242)
        Most of this roll is bus driver Jack Rader driving a bus through mid-Manhattan traffic.
      - Credits (Film canister c214, 16mm film reels 001_0164, 001_0165)
      - James Horst Interview and Clips (Box 18, Film canister c168, 16mm film reels 001_0368, 001_0369)
      - Railroad and Gas Workers (Film canister c76, 16mm film reels 001_0235)
        See the video reproduction cuid37015 in Subseries I.B.
        Railroad train maintenance workers; gas utility workers; Transport Workers Union's Railroad Division president talking with railroad workers.
      - Trims, circa 1930-1966 (Film canister c89, 16mm film reels 001_0233)
        Historical stock footage, including shots or scenes of: Miners; conflict between workers and troops, workers and police; poverty; inauguration of Franklin D. Roosevelt; Michael Quill's funeral.
      - Trims, 1953 (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0874)
        Michael Quill gives speech to Transport Workers Union mass meeting during 1953 New York City private bus lines strike.
      - Trims, May 19, 1960 (Film canister c85, 16mm film reels 001_0227)
        See the video reproduction cuid37012 in Subseries I.B.
        Includes N. Weissman Guinan speech, TWU HDQS, sign up for picket, pickets at Juniata shop
      - Trims, January, 1961 (Film canister c216, 16mm film reels 001_0347)
        Transport Workers Union program reporting on the proposed contract with the Philadelphia Transit Company to Local 234 members.
      - Trims, January 19, 1961 (Film canister c178, 16mm film reels 001_0178)
      - Trims, 1966 (Film canister c237, 16mm film reels 001_0159, Film canister c75, 16mm film reels 001_0306)
        See the video reproduction cuid1030 in Subseries I.B.
        Trims from Michael Quill's funeral service at St. Patrick's Cathedral.
      - Trims, 1966 (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0307)
        New York City Transit strike; location shots of San Francisco; gas storage tank.
      - Trims (Film canister c237, 16mm film reels 001_0156)
        Subway tunnels; subway station platforms
      - Trims (Film canister c237, 16mm film reels 001_0157)
      - Trims (Film canister c237, 16mm film reels 001_0158)
        Portions of press conference with Matthew Guinan announcing details of contract settlement.
      - Trims (Film canister c237, 16mm film reels 001_0160)
        The first few frames from a transport montage.
      - Trims (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0313)
        Includes shots of subway tunnels, subway station platforms, and a fashion show.
      - Trims (Box 17, Film canister c7, 16mm film reels 001_0379)
        Includes shots of a demonstration, as well as Fiorello LaGuardia and Michael Quill speaking at a rally.
      - Trims (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0875)
        Transport Workers Union officers inspect operation of automated subway train system.
      - Trims (Film canister c231, 16mm film reels 001_0092)
        Transport Workers Union officers addressing mass meeting; audience entering hall; audience reaction shots.
      - Trims (Film canister c231, 16mm film reels 001_0093)
        Transport Workers Union officer Matthew Guinan reports on progress of 1953 New York City private bus lines strike to mass meeting of membership.
      - Trims (Film canister c231, 16mm film reels 001_0091)
      - Trims (Film canister c231, 16mm film reels 001_0094, 001_0095)
        Transport Workers Union picket line outside a workplace gate.
      - Trims (Film canister c235, 16mm film reels 001_0029)
      - Trims (Box 25, 16mm film reels 001_0905)
        Trims of filmed press releases by the Transport Workers Union, many regarding their strike against the Pennsylvania Railroad.
      - Trims (Film canister c79, 16mm film reels 001_0317)
        Clips of trains, train passengers, unemployed workers.
      - Trims (Film canister c145, 16mm film reels 001_0221)
      - Trims (Film canister c196, 16mm film reels 001_0168, 001_0169)
      - Trims (Film canister c194, 16mm film reels 001_0058, 001_0059)
      - Trims (Film canister c105, 16mm film reels 001_0284)
        See the video reproduction cuid37013 in Subseries I.B.
        Includes shots of buses, bus garage, bus drivers, bus passengers in New York City; traffic and subway trains, subway train control room, subway train equipment in New York City; views of New York City from elevated subway train.
      - Trims (Box 27, 16mm film reels 001_0901)
        Includes shots of New York City skyline seen from an industrial waterfront; freight car at rest; tugboat; Transport Workers Union headquarters building; subway trains in motion; subway conductor Alex Murray; Douglas MacMahon, Matthew Guinan, Tom Costigan, and James Horst in staged shots; airport runway; bus driver.
      - Trims (Film canister c105, 16mm film reels 001_0284)
        Includes shots of subway trains.
      - Trims (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0814)
        Michael Quill makes a statement on the progress of American labor. V.O. by a narrator talking about the life of Philip Murray.
      - Trims (Film canister c230, 16mm film reels 001_0065, 001_0066, 001_0067, 001_0068, 001_0069, 001_0070, 001_0071, 001_0072, 001_0073, 001_0074, 001_0075, 16mm film reels 001_0076, 001_0077, 001_0078, 001_0079, 001_0080, 001_0081, 001_0082, 001_0083, 001_0084, 001_0085, 001_0086, 001_0087, 001_0088, 001_0089, 001_0090)
        These trims include footage of: airline stewardess; plane landing; airplane luggage; bus driver; subway operation; airplane mechanics; subway scenes; storefront; Costigan on camera. They are most likely trims from the film The Best is Yet to Come.
      - Trims (Film canister c232, 16mm film reels 001_0034, 001_0035, 001_0036, 001_0037, 001_0038, 001_0039, 001_0040, 001_0041, 001_0042, 001_0043, 001_0044, 001_0045, 16mm film reels 001_0046, 001_0047, 001_0048, 001_0049, 001_0050, 001_0051, 001_0052, 001_0053, 001_0054, 001_0055)
        These trims contain footage of subway and bus operators at work, as well as a trim of Michael Quill speaking. They are most likely trims from the film The Best is Yet to Come.
      - Trims (Film canister c233, 16mm film reels 001_0096, 001_0097, 001_0098, 001_0099, 001_0100, 001_0101, 001_0102, 001_0103, 001_0104, 001_0105, 001_0106, 16mm film reels 001_0107, 001_0108, 001_0109, 001_0110, 001_0111, 001_0112, 001_0113, 001_0114, 001_0116, 001_0117)
        These trims contain footage of bus operators, subway trains, airport workers, a picket line, and a closeup of filmmaker Tom Costigan. They are most likely trims from the film The Best is Yet to Come.
      - Trims (Film canister c234, 16mm film reels 001_0001, 001_0002, 001_0003, 001_0004, 001_0005, 001_0006, 001_0007, 001_0008, 001_0009, 001_0010, 001_0011, 001_0012, 16mm film reels 001_0013, 001_0014, 001_0015, 001_0016, 001_0017, 001_0018, 001_0019, 001_0020, 001_0021, 001_0022, 001_0023, 001_0024, 001_0025)
        These trims contain footage of subway and bus operators at work, and filmmaker Tom Costigan conducting interviews. They are most likely trims from the film The Best is Yet to Come.
      - Trims (Film canister c227, 16mm film reels 001_0772, 001_0773, 001_0774, 001_0775, 001_0776, 001_0777, 001_0778, 001_0779, 001_0780, 001_0781, 001_0782)
        These trims include footage of subway, bus, and airplane operators at work; they are most likely trims from the film The Best is Yet to Come.
      - Trims (Film canister c238, 16mm film reels 001_0118, 001_0119, 001_0120, 001_0121, 001_0122, 001_0123, 001_0124, 001_0125, 001_0126, 001_0127, 001_0128, 001_0129, 001_0130, 001_0131, 001_0132, 001_0133)
        These trims contain footage of bus operators at work, New York City Streets, a helicopter in flight, Ellis Van Riper, and filmmaker Tom Costigan conducting an interview with James Horst. They are most likely trims from the film The Best is Yet to Come.
    - 20th Anniversary Celebration, April 29, 1954 (Box 22, 16mm film reels 001_0431)
      Telecast (on the Dumont Network) of the Transport Workers Union's celebration of its twentieth anniversary, mass meeting held at St. Nicholas Arena in New York City, on the evening of April 29, 1954.
    - 20th Anniversary Celebration, April 29, 1954 (Film canister c29, 16mm film reels 001_0184)
    - "Save the 3rd Avenue El" Demonstration, circa 1954-1955 (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0819, 16mm film reels 001_0820)
      See the video reproduction cuid36993 in Subseries I.B.
      Picket line, "Save the 3rd Avenue El" demonstration by Transport Workers Union against destruction of elevated subway line.
    - Local 234 Settlement Announcement with Michael Quill, March, 1956 (Box 25, 16mm film reels 001_0821)
      Officers of Transport Workers Union Local 234 and Michael Quill of Transport Workers Union International urge local members to ratify new contract with Philadelphia Transportation Company.
    - Mayor Wagner at City Hall CIO Council Meeting, 1956 (Film canister c93, 16mm film reels 001_0230)
      New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr. makes speech to (New York City or New York State) CIO Council during his campaign for U.S. Senate.
    - Robert Wagner Campaign Speech, November, 1956 (Film canister c122, 16mm film reels 001_0255)
      See the video reproduction cuid37017 in Subseries I.B.
      Appeal to voters by New York City mayor Robert F. Wagner Jr. in the last days of his campaign for U.S. Senate
    - Robert Wagner Campaign Speech, 1956 (Box 33, 16mm film reels 001_0330)
      Campaign speech by Democratic-Liberal party candidate for United States Senate, New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner.
    - Sixth Annual Art Show of District 65, March, 1957 (Film canister c96, 16mm film reels 001_0331, 001_0332)
    - Michael Quill on NYC Transit Authority, September 17, 1957 (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0812)
      Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill demands New York City Transit Authority conduct a representation election among its employees.
    - A Memorial Tribute to Philip Murray, November 13, 1957
      The program contains a documentary biographical sequence, using voice-over narration, music, stills and stock footage, and a panel of Transport Workers Union officials and friends giving memorial tributes to Murray, broadcast from a television studio.
      - Film (Film canister c181, 16mm film reels 001_0326, Box 17, Film canister c33, 16mm film reels 001_0375)
      - Film (Box 31, 16mm film reels 001_0917)
      - Trims and Outtakes (Box 23, 16mm film reels 001_0813, Film canister c122, 16mm film reels 001_0253)
    - Private Bus Lines Strike -- Meeting Trims, November 26, 1957 (Box 16, Film canister c128, 16mm film reels 001_0388)
      Trims from private bus lines strike meeting held by Transport Workers Union.
    - Private Lines Strike Meeting, Henry Hudson Hotel, November 26, 1957 (Box 27, 16mm film reels 001_0903)
      November 26, 1957 mass meeting held at Henry Hudson Hotel in New York City, called by Transport Workers Union leadership to report to members on results of negotiations with eight privately operated bus companies in New York City.
    - Michael Quill Address, December, 1957 (Box 17, Film canister c111, 16mm film reels 001_0372, 001_0373)
      Michael Quill addresses Transport Workers Union mass meeting.
    - Local 100 Bus Strike Authorization, December, 1957 (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0816)
      At the Manhattan Center, Transport Workers Union Local 100 members vote to authorize a strike against private bus lines in the New York City metropolitan area.
    - Voting in Transit Election, December 16, 1957 (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0815)
    - Lines Strike Meeting, circa 1957 (Film canister c129, 16mm film reels 001_0250, 001_0251)
      Transport Workers Union mass meeting with vote and speech by Matthew Guinan.
    - Meeting of Presidents with TWU and Pennsylvania Railroad, circa 1957
      Transport Workers Union officials present the union's complaints against the management of the Pennsylvania Railroad to a meeting of presidents of 51 Railroad Division locals.
      - Film (Film canister c136, 16mm film reels 001_0175)
      - Film (Box 19, Film canister c120, 16mm film reels 001_0420)
      - Film (Film canister c127, 16mm film reels 001_0274)
      - Film (Film canister c135, 16mm film reels 001_0298)
      - Film (Box 16, Film canister c128, 16mm film reels 001_0390)
      - Film (Box 17, Film canister c35, 16mm film reels 001_0383)
    - Labor Day Parade, AFL-CIO, September 7, 1959 (Film canister c169, 16mm film reels 001_0203)
      See the video reproduction cuid36994 in Subseries I.B.
      A documentary with voiceover narration, music, and synch sound. The film depicts an AFL-CIO Labor Day Parade and its organziation.
    - Mass Meeting, Local 100 Rally, December 27, 1959 (Film canister c152, 16mm film reels 001_0213, Box 25, 16mm film reels 001_0872)
      TWU Local 100 mass meeting to vote on authorizing a strike (to commence January 1, 1960) against both the city of New York and the city's seven private bus lines. Speakers include Matthew Guinan, John Howell, Frank Sheehan, Harry Van Arsdale Jr., and Michael Quill.
    - Van Arsdale Speaks at Mass Meeting, December 27, 1959 (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0871)
      New York City Central Labor Council's Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. addresses mass meeting of Transport Workers Union Local 100.
    - Press Release on NYCTA Negotiations, 1957 (Film canister c209, 16mm film reels 001_0170)
      Filmed press release of announcements by Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill on contract demands presented by the union to the New York City Transit Authority.
    - Local 100 Mass Meeting and Strike Resolution, 1959 (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0870)
      Mass meeting of Local 100 Transport Workers Union; Michael Quill reads aloud resolution for a bus strike.
    - Mass Meeting, Local Meeting, 1959 (Box 23, 16mm film reels 001_0832)
      Outtakes and trims from several films, including: trims from a mayoral campaign film for Robert F. Wagner, Jr.; low-angle shots of feet and shoes of New Yorkers and traffic, filmed in midtown Manhattan in the 1950's; shots of buses and bus driver; outtakes from Transport Workers Union's film on the 1953 New York City bus strike, Twenty-Nine Days to Victory; a "Save the El" demonstration; a take for a filmed press release by Michael Quill; negotiations.
    - Mass Meeting on NYCTA Strike, circa 1959 (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0866)
      Mass meeting of the Transport Workers Union during a strike against New York City Transit Authority.
    - Press Conference on NYCTA Collective Bargaining, circa 1959 (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0873, Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0867)
      Press conference by Michael Quill; he announces a deadlock in collective bargaining between the New York City Transit Authority and Transport Workers Union.
    - Press Conference on NYCTA Collective Bargaining, circa 1959 (Film canister c115, 16mm film reels 001_0239, 001_0240)
    - Michael Quill Press Conference on Wildcat Strike, circa 1959 (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0864, 001_0865)
      Press conference by Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill on wildcat strike by Transport Workers Union bus drivers.
    - Michael Quill Railroad Strike Announcement, circa 1959 (Film canister c109, 16mm film reels 001_0325)
      Michael Quill announces a strike by Transport Workers Union against the Pennsylvania Railroad.
    - Mayor Robert Wagner Election Speech, circa 1959-1960 (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0868)
      New York City mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr., delivers a primary election campaign speech at a meeting of the Transport Workers Union.
    - Michael Quill Press Conferences, 1959-1963 (Film canister c116, 16mm film reels 001_0340)
      One press release regarding nationalization of railroads, and one press conference on NYCTA collective bargaining.
    - Press Release on Railroad Strikes, January 21, 1960 (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0826)
      Four copies of the same film clip in which Michael Quill answers a reporter's questions about a strike threatened by the Transport Workers Union against the Pennsylvania and New York Central Railroads.
    - Wayne Morse on Kennedy-Landrum-Griffen Bill, January 22, 1960 (Box 19, Film canister c95, 16mm film reels 001_0416)
      United States Senator Wayne Morse speaks out against the Kennedy-Landrum-Griffin bill and against Senator John F. Kennedy for Kennedy's sponsorship of the bill and for his machinations on behalf of it. Morse promises to continue fighting the bill by attempting to amend it.
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Strike Announcement, August, 1960 (Film canister c109, 16mm film reels 001_0324)
      Michael Quill announces Transport Workers Union strike against Pennsylvania Railroad.
    - Why Pennsylvania Railroad Strike?, August 31, 1960
      Television program announcing the calling of the 1960 Transport Workers Union strike against the Pennsylvania Railroad, and explaining the reasons for the strike.
      - Opening segment (Film canister c162, 16mm film reels 001_0181)
        Opening of the television program, Why Pennsylvania Railroad Strike? and Michael Quill's announcement of the strike call.
      - Film (Film canister c115, 16mm film reels 001_0237)
      - Film (Film canister c212, 16mm film reels 001_0906)
      - Film (Box 18, Film canister c165, 16mm film reels 001_0357)
      - Film (Box 17, Film canister c45, 16mm film reels 001_0380)
    - Labor Day Parade, September, 1960 (Film canister c131, 16mm film reels 001_0266)
      Transport Workers Union's participation in 1960 New York City Labor Day parade, including demonstration against the Pennsylvania Railroad.
    - Local 234 Negotiations with the Philadelphia Transportation Company, September, 1960 (Box 34, 16mm film reels 001_0319)
      Material related to negotiations between the Transport Workers Union Local 234 and the Philadelphia Transportation Company.
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Strike, September, 1960 (Film canister c110, 16mm film reels 001_0353)
      This footage appears to have been shot to demonstrate the effectiveness of Transport Workers Union's strike against the Pennsylvania Railroad.
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Strike, September, 1960 (Film canister c81, 16mm film reels 001_0224)
    - District 65 at Labor Day Parade, September 4, 1960 (Film canister c124, 16mm film reels 001_0241)
    - Automated Subway Train, circa 1960 (Film canister c113, 16mm film reels 001_0282)